Guide to the Philo-Celtic Society Records AIA.092
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Philo-Celtic Society Records
1878-1964
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Philo-Celtic Society
Norton, Jim
AIA.092
3.26 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box
The New York Philo-Celtic Society (also referred to as the Philo-Celtic Society and Cumann Carad na Gaeilge) is a North American society whose mission is to encourage and advance the use of the Irish language. The society was founded in 1872 in the broader context of the Gaelic revival, a period of renewed interest in the Irish language and Irish cultural practices. In the fall of 1872, Mícheál Ó Lócháin started free Irish language instruction classes (called "Philo-Celtic class") held at Our Lady of Victory School in Brooklyn, New York, where he served as principal. In 1874 Ó Lócháin and his friends formally organized the second Philo-Celtic Society in Brooklyn. In 1878, the Manhattan members of the Brooklyn group organized the third Philo-Celtic Society, the New York Philo-Celtic Society. The Society collaborated alongside other similar groups as part of the Council of Gaelic Societies of New York, and was an affiliated branch of the Gaelic League of Ireland, with its primary focus on the advancement and renaissance of the Irish language. In the mid-20th century, the New York Philo-Celtic Society moved its operations from Manhattan to Long Island City to Mineaola, and experienced a decline in participation and support as membership interest more strongly favored social and cultural aspects of Ireland rather than the Irish language. In 2004, the Philo-Celtic Society reorganized, admitted new members, and reaffirmed its central commitment to the support and practice of the Irish language.The New York Philo-Celtic Society Records (dated 1878-1964) consists of materials created and collected by the Society documenting their mission, membership, and administrative operations. Materials include memoranda, meeting minutes, correspondence, membership lists and ledgers, financial records, programs and other event ephemera, self-published newsletters and magazines, ephemera documenting ceili and theatrical productions, and Irish language learning and teaching materials, including syllabi, poems, songs, and textbooks. The collection documents not only the organization's activities, but the broader context of the Gaelic revival of the late 19th century, with particular emphasis on its manifestation amongst Irish Americans in the New York City area. The materials document a concerted effort amongst Irish Americans to learn and practice Irish language and cultural forms, such as dance and sports.
Scope and Contents
The New York Philo-Celtic Society Records (dated 1878-1964) consists of materials created and collected by the Society documenting their mission, membership, and administrative operations. Materials include memoranda, meeting minutes, correspondence, membership lists and ledgers, financial records, programs and other event ephemera, self-published newsletters and magazines, ephemera documenting ceili and theatrical productions, and Irish language learning and teaching materials, including syllabi, poems, songs, and textbooks. The collection documents not only the organization's activities, but the broader context of the Gaelic revival of the late 19th century, with particular emphasis on its manifestation amongst Irish Americans in the New York City area. The materials document a concerted effort amongst Irish Americans to learn and practice Irish language and cultural forms, such as dance and sports.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jim Norton (Séamus Ó Neachtain) in August 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2024.051.
Historical Note
The New York Philo-Celtic Society (also referred to as the Philo-Celtic Society and Cumann Carad na Gaeilge) is a North American society whose mission is to encourage and advance the use of the Irish language.
The society was founded in 1872 in the broader context of the Gaelic revival, a period of renewed interest in the Irish language and Irish cultural practices. In the fall of 1872, Mícheál Ó Lócháin started free Irish language instruction classes (called "Philo-Celtic class") held at Our Lady of Victory School in Brooklyn, New York, where he served as principal. In 1874 Ó Lócháin and his friends formally organized the second Philo-Celtic Society in Brooklyn (the first being in Boston in 1873). In 1878, the Manhattan members of the Brooklyn group organized the third Philo-Celtic Society, the New York Philo-Celtic Society (Brooklyn and Manhattan Societies later merged in 1945). Ó Lócháin began publication of An Gaodhal ("The Gaelic Speaker") in 1881, which served as the Society's bi-lingual monthly magazine until it ceased publication in 1904. The Society collaborated alongside other similar groups as part of the Council of Gaelic Societies of New York, and was an affiliated branch of the Gaelic League of Ireland, with its primary focus on the advancement and renaissance of the Irish language. In 1891, Irish language scholar (and eventual first President of Ireland) Douglas Hyde visited the New York Philo-Celtic Society and its classes.
In the mid-20th century, the New York Philo-Celtic Society moved its operations from Manhattan to Long Island City to Mineaola, and experienced a decline in participation and support as membership interest more strongly favored social and cultural aspects of Ireland rather than the Irish language. In 2004, the Philo-Celtic Society reorganized, admitted new members, and reaffirmed its central commitment to the support and practice of the Irish language. Online language courses began in 2006, and expanded to included video classes in the fall of 2020.The Society publishes a quarterly literary magazine called An Gael, which has been edited by Séamas Ó Neachtain since 2009.
Source:
Correspondence with Jerry Kelly, Rúnaí Ábhai Scoile (Curriculum Secretary) of the New York Philo-Celtic Society
Irish language |z United States; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish language -- History -- 20th century.; Irish literature.; Irish language -- Revival; Norton, Jim
- Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Administrative Records, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Constitution and Proposed Amendments, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1947-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Correspondence and Meeting Minutes, 1950-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Financial Records, 1910-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Gaelic Leagues Football Club Minute Book, 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Irish Language -- Pedagogical Materials, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Irish Language -- Texts, 1906-1958 (Box 2, Folder 6-9, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
- Ledger, 1888-1895 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Ledger, 1889-1890 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Ledger, 1896-1906 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Ledger, 1920-1928 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Meetings, 1954-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Minute Book, 1878-1890 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Minute Book, 1915-1918 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Minute Book, 1911-1920 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Minute Book, 1920-1929 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Pages from Ledgers and Minute Books, 1880, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Report on Irish Language Schools and Programs, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Social and Cultural Events, 1900-1964 (Box 4, Folder 7, Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- The Traitor Script, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Transcribed Poetry (Sean Ó Conaill), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)